Guide to the Roy M. Huffington Ambassadorial Papers, 1988-2008 MS 617
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Roy M. Huffington Ambassadorial Papers, 1988-2008
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Huffington, Roy M.
MS 617
9 Linear Feet 10 boxes
This collection is part of a wider compilation of Roy M. Huffington's personal and professional papers. Specifically, these papers encompass Huffington's appointment and work as Ambassador to Austria, as well as the numerous political, personal, and business connections he made while serving in Vienna.
Biographical Sketch
Roy M. Huffington was born in Tomball, Texas on Oct 4, 1917. The son of an oil man, he earned his bachelors in geology from Southern Methodist University in 1938, and earned a Ph.D. in geology from Harvard in 1942. After serving aboard the USS Hornet as a lieutenant during World War II, he left the Navy and went to work for Humble Oil. In 1956, Huffington left Humble to start his own business with the money he had saved over the previous decade, Roy M. Huffington, Inc. or as it was also known as, "Huffco". The company made a number of successful ventures around the world, most notably the discovery of vast reserves of natural gas in Indonesia in 1972. In 1989, Huffington sold his oil company, and in 1990 President Bush appointed him to Ambassador to Austria. Among his many other commitments he also served as chairman of the Asia Society and the Salzburg Seminar. Huffington passed away in 2008 at the age of 90.
Scope and Contents
This collection is a subset of a wider gathering of Roy M. Huffington's personal and professional papers. The materials here reflect his time as Ambassador to Austria and the many connections made during his appointment. It includes office records, reports, correspondence, and photographs from the American embassy in Austria, as well as records from the Salzburg Institute, Geological Society of America Foundation, and the American Austrian Foundation.
Series are composed of records mostly in their original order, though some records were rearranged to reflect their significance or to create more intuitive groupings. While the first series pertains specifically to Huffington's service as Ambassador to Austria, all but one of the subsequent series are based on particular organizations, such as the Salzburg Seminar and the Council of American Ambassadors. Users of this collection should bear in mind that while Huffington's involvement with most of these organizations began due to his service as Ambassador, his interest and involvement in them continued well past the end of his appointment, and consequently the bulk of the records of these series were not generated during that time.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Related Materials
Please refer to Roy M. Huffington Personal and Professional papers,1972-2009, MS 688; Roy M. Huffington Naval Papers, 1942-2005 MS 611 for more information on the Navy and Mr. Huffington; Huffington Oil company records, 1977-2006 MS 575; as well as the Huffington and allied families' papers, 1650-1955 MS 883.
Index Terms
Subjects
Politics and government; Ambassadors; Social life and customs
Places
Austria; Austria -- Vienna; Austria -- Salzburg
Subjects (Persons)
Huffington, Roy M.
- Series I: Ambassadorship Materials, 1989-1994
  - Subseries A: Appointment, 1989-1990
    - The Ambassadorial Seminar, 1989-12-11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Farewell Party- Mike Huffington Host Washington DC, 1990-04-05 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Swearing in Ceremony, Washington D.C., 1990-08-16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - United Methodist Church of Vienna, Welcome to Vienna (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Ambassadorship – General (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: U.S. State Department, 1988-1992
    - U.S. Department of State- Ambassadorial Training (I) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - U.S. Department of State- Ambassadorial Training (II) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - US Department of State - Ambassadorial Training (III) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - U.S. Department of State - Ambassadorial Training (IV) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - U.S. Department of State- Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - U.S. Department of State- Directories (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - U.S. Department of State (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - U.S. Department of State- Forms (I) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - U.S. Department of State- Forms (II) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - U.S. Department of State- Forms (III) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Subseries C: American Embassy, Vienna, Austria, 1990-2007
    - Briefing book for the Ambassador (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - American Embassy- Vienna Austria (I) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American Embassy- Vienna Austria (II) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - American Embassy- Vienna Austria (III) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - American Embassy- Vienna Austria (IV) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - American Embassy- Vienna Austria (V) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - American Embassy- Vienna Austria (VI) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - American Embassy- Art in Embassies program (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Schedules (I) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Schedules (II) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - American Embassy- Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Invitations (I) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Invitations (II) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Government Officials (I) (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Government Officials (II) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Visitors- Vienna (I) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Visitors- Vienna (II) (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Listings: Congressional Staff- Directories (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Farewell Letters: Roy M. Huffington (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Farewell Letters (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Subseries D: Projects, Conferences, and Events, 1990-1993
    - Access- Central Eastern European Markets- Manual, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Danube Basin Conference II, Vienna Austria, 1992-06-01-1992-06-02 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Danube Basin Conference Brochures Publications, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Danube Basin Conference III, Budapest Hungary (Canceled), 1993-06-19-1993-06-22 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - US Department of Commerce (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - United Nations Industrial Development Organization (UNIDO) (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Verbund Plan (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Vienna Opera Ball (I) (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Vienna Opera Ball (II) (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Harvard Club of Austria Vienna Event, 1992-05-21 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - US international Trade Commission (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Trip to New York Meeting with Dr. Alois Mock, 1993-09-27-1993-09-29 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Ward Howell International Inc. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Vienna Document, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Subseries E: Dinners and Receptions, 1990-1993
    - American Embassy Residence- Reception/Dinners (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Guest Book, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Guest Book, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Guest Book, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Guest Book, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Lists - Diners, Lunches, and Receptions (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Lists - Diners, Lunches, and Receptions (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Subseries F: Embassy Personnel
    - Embassy Residence Personnel Lists (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - American Embassy Employee Lists (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Embassy of the United States Applications (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Embassy of the US – Residency Renovation (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Subseries G Articles:, 1990-2003
    - Articles: Roy M. Huffington (I) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Articles: Roy M. Huffington (II) (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Articles: Austria (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Articles: Miscellaneous Reading (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Subseries H: Graphic Material, 1990-1994
    - Framed certificate, Roy M. Huffington, Ambassador to Republic of Austria. Signed by President George Bush and James Baker, III, Secretary of State, August 6, 1990 (Drawer 126)
    - Outstanding Community Service. The College Republic SJSU, the Santa Clara County Republican Central Committee, the Santa Clara County Young Republican's, et al. Ambassador Roy M. Huffington, October 24, 1994 (Drawer 127)
    - The United States flag and crew patch flown aboard the Orbiter "Challenger," STS 51-B, April 29-May 6, 1985. Photographs and flag mounted on board, inscribed to Roy Huffington, US Ambassador to Austria, May 3, 1991 (Drawer 127)
    - Crew patches flown aboard Orbiter "Challenger," STS-8, August 30-September 5, 1983 and Space Shuttle "Columbia," STS-52, October 22-November 1, 1992. Photographs and crew patches mounted on board, presented to Ambassador Roy M. Huffington from National Aeronautics and Space Administration. (Box 127)
    - Poster for Davis Cup Osterreich-USA competition, inscribed to Ambassador Huffington and signed by US + Austria Davis Cup Teams (Drawer 127)
    - Poster: "Baldinger: This is not America, nor is it Roy Huffington." Art Exhibition March 19, 1993-April 22, 1993. (Drawer 127)
    - Glass Plate with DER Landeshauptmann von Tirol etched in center. Housed in case. (Drawer 128)
    - Marine Security Detachments, Guest of Honor Ambassador Roy M. Huffington, Marine Corps Ball, Vienna, Austria, 1992 (Box 128)
    - "Stadt Ferlach" Memento flag from the town of Ferlach with coat of arms., n.d. (Drawer 128)
    - Certificate for the "Medal of Honour" of the Institute of International Relations of Kyiv National Taras Shevchenko University (Drawer 128)
    - Commemorative medal, "Institute of International Relations, Kyiv Taras Shevchenko National University" (Drawer 128)
- Series II: Salzburg Seminar, 1980-2004
  - Salzburg Seminar: Correspondence (I), 1980-2004 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Correspondence (II), 1980-2004 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Correspondence (III), 1908-2004 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Correspondence (IV), 1980-2004 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Correspondence (V), 1980-2004 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Correspondence (VI), 1980-2004 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Correspondence (VII), 1980-2004 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Correspondence (VIII), 1980-2004 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Correspondence (IX), 1980-2004 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Correspondence (X), 1980-2004 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Salzburg Seminar- Correspondence (I), 2005 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Salzburg Seminar- Correspondence (II), 2005 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Salzburg Seminar- Correspondence (III), 2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Salzburg Seminar 50th Anniversary Celebration Salzburg, Austria, (I), 1997-06-25-1997-06-29 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Salzburg Seminar 50th Anniversary Celebration, Salzburg, Austria (II), 1997-06-25-1997-06-29 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Salzburg Seminar 50th Anniversary Celebration, Salzburg, Austria (III), 1997-06-25-1997-06-29 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Board Directoy (I) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Board Directoy (II) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Salzburg Seminar Roster (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - University of Salzburg, 2001-05 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Programs, 1993-1999, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Salzburg Seminar- Holocaust Issue, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Visit with Ray Nasher, 2001-12 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Salzburg Seminar- State Department Visit- Washington, D.C., 2003-07-07-2003-07-08 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Contributions (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Salzburg Seminar: Meierhof Renovation Donations (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Series III: Council of American Ambassadors, 1992-2008
  - Council of American Ambassadors (I), 2005-2008 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Council of American Ambassadors (II), 1995-2005 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Council of American Ambassadors (III), 1993-1995 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Council of American Ambassadors Spring 2008 Conference / 25th Anniversary Gala Washington DC, 2008-05-04-2008-05-07 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Council of American Ambassadors – Mission to Moscow, Kiev and Bratislava (I), 2005-09-14-2005-09-28 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Council of American Ambassadors – Mission to Moscow, Kiev and Bratislava (II), 2005-09-14-2005-09-28 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Council of American Ambassadors – Mission to Moscow, Kiev and Bratislava (III), 2005-09-14-2005-09-28 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Council of American Ambassadors – The Review, Fall 1992 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Council of American Ambassadors – Membership Directory, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Austrian Foundation, 1993-2008
  - The American Austrian Foundation, Inc. General Correspondence (I) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - The American Austrian Foundation, Inc. General Correspondence (II) (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - The American Austrian Foundation, Inc. General Correspondence (III) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - The American Austrian Foundation, Inc. General Correspondence (IV) (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - The American Austrian Foundation, Inc. General Correspondence (V) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The American Austrian Foundation – Directory (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The American Austrian Foundation, Inc. Contributions (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Series V: The Geological Society of America Foundation, 1989
  - The Geological Society of America Foundation (I) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - The Geological Society of America Foundation (II) (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - The Geological Society of America Foundation (III) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - The Geological Society of America Foundation (IV) (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series VI: Post-Appointment Trips, Events, and Connections, 1994-2006
  - Genetics Policy Institute (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Meeting with George H.W. Bush, Kennebunkport, 2001-07-23 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Embassy to the Republic of Austria Luncheon Honoring Ambassador Eva Novotney, Houston Club, 2004-11-22 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Vranitzky, Franz- Fulbright Award, Washington D.C., 1995-11-10-1995-11-11 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Klestil, Thomas Luncheon, New York City, 1995-10-20 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Trip to Vienna, Austria Business Diplomatic Meetings, 1997-06-29-1997-07-03 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Trip to Vienna, Austria - Business Development/ Diplomatic, 1998-06-28-1998-07-06 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Trip to Vienna, Austria, 1999-06-27-1999-06-30 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - J.E. Sheenan Co. Inc. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Vienna Diplomatic Academy (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Vienna Boys Choir (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Unknown Book by Mo Yaka (Japanese) (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Series VII: Addenda
  - Ambassador Huffington's Invitation to His Residence for Tennis Professionals, VHS, 1990-09-20 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - RMH Award Ceremony - Vienna, Austria, 1997-11-30-1997-12-04 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Personal (Part 1) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Personal (Part 2) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "Congratulations" Letters (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Chamber of Commerce (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Casinos - Austria (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Letters and News, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Grand Decoration in Gold for Merits About the Republic of Austria, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Trip to Vienna, Austria Business Development, 1994-06-24-1994-07-05 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Austrian Trade Commission in the United States (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Austrian Press and Information Service (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Austrian Embassy: General (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Austrian Cultural Institute (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Austrian Consulate General: New York (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Austrian Consulate General: Houston (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Speeches Part 1 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Speeches Part 2 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Tuerk Dinner Honoring RMH/PGH/MH/AH Embassy of Austria - D.C., 1995-10-12 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Tuerk Trip - Austin Tx (Meeting with Gov. Richards), 1993-11-02 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Tuerk, H.E. Dr. Helmut Visit to Houston, 1993-11-02 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Oesterricherische National Bank (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - OMV (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - RMH Houston party Invitations - Houston County Club, 1990-08-24 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Roy M. Huffington Reception - Sacher Hotel, Vienna, Austria, 1994-06-29 (Box 8, Folder 27)
- Series VIII: Media (Box 9)
  - Cassette tapes
    - Broadcast David Ward "Radio Austria International" - Interview with Amb. Huffington, 1990-10-14
    - Amb. Huffington BDR (Blue Danube Radio), 1991-01-03
    - CD Radio - Amb. Huffington, 1991-03-11
    - Amb. Huffington BDR (Blue Danube Radio) - 2 tapes, 1991-03-22
    - BDR (Blue Danube Radio), 1991-06-12
    - The Honorable Roy M. Huffington interview with Charles Stuart Kennedy for the Foreign Affairs Oral History Program - 2 cassette tapes and transcript, 1999-03-26
  - Video
    - United States Information Service. Zeit Im Bild VHS, 1991-01-08
    - United States Information Service. Vien Heute. VHS, 1991-01-28
    - Amb. Roy M. Huffington Vienna Welcoming Dinner in Graz, Austria VHS, 1991-04-29
    - United States Information Service. Orf Seitnblicke VHS, 1991-05-02
    - United States Information Service. Inlandsreport VHS, 1991-10-10
    - United States Information Service. John McLaughlin: One on One VHS, 1991-10-13
    - United States Information Service. Opernball 1992 VHS
    - United States Information Service. Opera Ball Coverage VHS, 1992-02-28-1992-03-01
    - United States Information Service. Oesterreichbild VHS, 1992-04-25
    - United States Information Service. Seitenblicke revue VHS, 1992-05-03
    - Roy M. Huffington - Vienna America Exhibit VHS, 1992-05-03
    - United States Information Service. Orf Zeit Im Bild VHS, 1992-06-30
    - United States Information Service. Good Morning America VHS, 1992-07-10
    - Broadcast News Reports. Houston Symphony in Europe VHS, 1992-12-22
    - Opernball 1993 VHS
    - United States Information Service. Ambassador Huffington in Austria VHS, 1990-1993
    - Roy M. Huffington - Vienna - How to do business in eastern Europe VHS, n.d.
    - Good Morning America - Salzburg Music and Vienna Economy VHS, n.d.
    - Hello Austria - Hello Vienna VHS, n.d.
    - World Video Travel Guide - Vienna, n.d.
- Series IX: Oversize Materials
  Separated Materials
  Some oversize photographs, certificates, plauques, and awards are housed in map drawers 126. Please see finding aid for UA 226: Rice University architectural drawings, oversize manuscript material, maps and photographs for individual items.
  - Commemorative medal, "Institute of International Relations, Kyiv Taras Shevchenko National University (Box 10, Item 1)
  - Photograph - Roy M. Huffington and Dick Thornburgh - Secretary of the Department of Justice, Washington, D.C., April 16, 1991 (Box 10, Item 2)
  - Plaque: Roy M. Huffington Wing, Salzburg Seminar, June 23, 2001 (Box 10, Item 3)
  - Framed certificate, Roy M. Huffington, Ambassador to Republic of Austria. Signed by President George Bush and James Baker, III, Secretary of State, August 6, 1990 (Box 10, Item 4)
  - Diplomatic Club. "Botschafter des Jahres," Ambassador of the Year, 1992 (Box 10, Item 5)
  - Crew patches flown aboard Orbiter "Challenger," STS-8, August 30-September 5, 1983 and Space Shuttle "Columbia," STS-52, October 22-November 1, 1992. Photographs and crew patches mounted on board, presented to Ambassador Roy M. Huffington from National Aeronautics and Space Administration. (Box 10, Item 6)
  - The United States flag and crew patch flown aboard the Orbiter "Challenger," STS 51-B, April 29-May 6, 1985. Photographs and flag mounted on board, inscribed to Roy Huffington, US Ambassador to Austria, May 3, 1991 (Box 10, Item 7)
  - Poster: "Baldinger: This is not America, nor is it Roy Huffington." Art Exhibition, March 19, 1993-April 22 (Box 10, Item 8)